Guide to the Papers of Herbert J. Adickes 1943-1945, 1970 (Bulk 1943-1945) MS 672.1
New-York Historical Society
Herbert J. Adickes papers
1943-1945, 1970 (Bulk 1943-1945)
New-York Historical Society
Adickes, Herbert J.
MS 672.1
1.5 Linear feet
The Adickes Papers are a collection of approximately 300 letters from Herbert J. Adickes to his girlfriend, later his wife, Virginia Miller, from January 1943 to April 1945.
Provenance
Donated by Edward Herpel, March 1997.
Access Restrictions
Open to qualified researchers.
Photocopying undertaken by staff only. Limited to twenty exposures of stable, unbound material per day. (Researchers may not accrue unused copy amounts from previous days.) See guidelines in Reading Room for details.
Biographical Note
Herbert J. Adickes and Virginia Miller met when Miller was a member of the Jack Cole Dancers touring troupe, and they married in 1943. Adickes joined the Marine Corps, apparently in March of 1944. He was stationed stateside for the duration of the war, and his letters continue first from Parris Island, SC and later from Camp LeJeune, NC.
Scope and Content Note
Adickes wrote to his wife Virginia almost daily, sometimes twice a day, about adjusting to military life, the weather, and how life in the South is different from New York. His letters express concern for his wife's health, and often mention how happy he will be when the war is over and they are reunited.
Adickes most often dated his letters with the day of the week, not the date of the month. Therefore the letters are arranged chronologically according to the date on the accompanying envelope. Undated letters without an accompanying envelope can be found in Box 3, folder 3.
There are several letters from friends arranged within the chronology, some V-mail and telegrams. The latest item in the collection is a letter from Herbert and Virginia's daughter, Merrill, dated May 1970, discussing her plans to marry in July of that year. Also included in the collection are greeting cards on the occasion of Herbert and Virginia's marriage and various holidays.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged chronologically.
The letters and cards are located in 3 boxes.
New York (N.Y.) -- Social life and customs -- 20th century.; Telegrams.; Soldiers.; Greeting cards; V-mail; Correspondence.; Southern States -- Social life and customs -- 20th century.; Camp Lejeune (N.C.).; World War, 1939-1945 -- Personal narratives, American.; Adickes, Virginia; Parris Island (S.C.: Recruit depot); United States. Marine Corps -- Military life
- Correspondence and Greeting Cards
  Scope and Contents note
  Incoming and outgoing correspondence of Herbert J. Adickes.
  - Correspondence, 1943 Jan.-1943 Feb. (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence, 1943 Mar.-1943 Nov. (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence, 1944 Mar.-1944 Apr. (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence, 1944 May (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence, 1944 June (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence, 1944 July (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence, 1944 Aug. (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence, 1944 Sept. (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence, 1944 Oct. (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence, 1944 Nov. (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence, 1944 Dec. (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence, 1945 Mar.-1945 Apr. (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence, [1945] (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence, 1970 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Greeting Cards, [1943-1945] (Box 3, Folder 3)